It goes back probably before the Stoics,
if we're being honest, but my favorite
formulation of it is in Nietzsche, where
he's talking about amor fati, translates
into love of fate. It's the idea that so
many traditions in the religious
sectors, or just in our everyday lived
experience, are renunciative. They aim
at denying some aspect of ourselves or
of reality in an attempt to try to make
it better. Nietzsche said amor fati is
how he is going to live his life
henceforth. He decided everything he is
going to say yes to. He will be a
yes-sayer, is what he says. This is an
affirmative stance towards reality,
where even if things are bad, or
uncomfortable, or horrible, we're going
to affirm reality as it is, and not
idealize it into something that it's
not. It's very common for people to do,
even when they're not religious, is to
think of reality as though it owes you
something. But, to affirm reality fully
is to accept the good, the bad, it's not
to rationalize about it, and to try to
make excuses for it, or frame your
suffering in a way where it makes it go
away. To truly affirm life and reality
is just to be in it, and to have life
itself be enough, truly.